<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <meta revision="$Id: cleaner.xml 736 2004-11-25 11:57:48Z spyromus $"/>
  <properties>
    <author email="spyromus@users.sourceforge.net">Aleksey Gureev</author>
    <title>Cleaner</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="General">

      <p>The goal of Cleaner module is very trivial -- to provide convenient multi-threaded
      cleanup for your channels collection.</p>

      <p>Cleaner is very similar to Poller in some manner. It uses Observers to fire events
      notifications, but instead of Approvers it uses Matchers to make a decisions.</p>

      <p>In order to make use of Cleaner you create it, add Observers and Matchers you need and
      start to register channels. In the following sections we will walk through all these steps.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Module structure">

      <p>Module is located at the package <b>de.nava.informa.utils.cleaner</b>.</p>

      <ul>

        <li><i>Cleaner</i> - the main class and central access point to all of Cleaner services.
        </li>

        <li><i>CleanerMatcherIF</i> - interface for Matcher implementations.</li>

        <li><i>PollerObserverIF</i> - interface for Observer implementations.</li>

      </ul>

      <p>In addition there is additional convenience class provided for transferring changes into
      Informa persistent storage. <i>PersistenceObserver</i> listens to all events coming from
      Cleaner and performs consequent changes to underlying storage using manager specified on
      construction. Note that if you plan to use it instances of channels Cleaner will be dealing
      with should be produced by Persistence Manager. Otherwise they will not be understood by it
      and you can get confusing results.</p>

    </section>

    <section name="Working with Cleaner">

      <section name="Initialization">

        <p>There&apos;s special rules you need to know to initialize your Cleaner copy.
        Here&apos;s the code for that:</p>

        <source>Cleaner cleaner = new Cleaner();</source>

        <p>Default period of cleans is set to one hour. You can change it and we will show a bit
        later how.</p>

        <p>Cleaner is capable of doing its work in multiple threads. Doing so it dramatically
        increases performance. Default value of number of working threads is
        determined by underlying scheduler. At the moment of this writing the default is set to
	<i>5</i> threads, but it may change, though it&apos;s not likely to. In most cases you
	do not need to deal with such a details, but if you really need full control over that you
	can specify number of working threads on creation or change it at run-time.</p>

<source>
// Here we create a single-threaded Cleaner
Cleaner cleaner = new Cleaner(1);

// Here we change number of threads to 3
cleaner.setWorkerThreads(3);</source>

        <p>You should note that change from bigger number of threads down to smaller can take some
        time. It&apos;s not time of the method call itself, but a time of transition. It works
        this way because the threads requiring to be removed can be busy with processing at the
        time of change and engine will wait for completion before killing them.</p>

      </section>

      <section name="Observers">

        <p>Observers receive notifications on interesting events:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>start of cleaning;</li>
          <li>finish of cleaning;</li>
          <li>finding of unwanted items.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>Another note is that Cleaner is not removing items from the channels for itself. One of
        your observers should take care of it.</p>

        <p>Once you have instance of Cleaner you need to register at least one observer to make it
        useful. Here&apos;s the piece of code:</p>

<source>
Cleaner cleaner = new Cleaner();

// Create and register observer
CleanerObserverIF observer = new MyObserver();
cleaner.addObserver(observer);</source>

        <p>You may need to remove some observer from the list and you can do it this way:</p>

        <source>cleaner.removeObserver(observer);</source>

      </section>

      <section name="Matchers">

        <p>Matchers act as decision-makers. During cleaning each item present in the channel passed
        to registered Matchers for review. It&apos;s enough to have even <i>single</i> vote to
        decide that item is unwanted and fire necessary event to Observers.</p>

        <p>Adding and removing of matchers is also simple:</p>

<source>
// Adding new matcher
CleanerMatcherIF matcher = new MyMatcher();
cleaner.addApprover(matcher);

// Removing approver
cleaner.removeMatcher(matcher);</source>

      </section>

      <section name="Registering and unregistering channels">

        <p>The next step after you have created Cleaner instance and set all necessary observers
        and matchers is to register some channels. When you register channel Cleaner contacts
        underlying scheduler to create plan of cleans for the channel. The first checking of
	the channel will start right after that.</p>

<source>
// Register channel with default cleaning period
cleaner.registerChannel(channel);</source>

        <p>By default, Cleaner uses its global period setting (which is equal to one hour) to
        initialize channel and build the cleans plan with scheduler, but you may wish to specify
        your own period for each particular channel.</p>

<source>
// Register channel with cleaning period set to 10 minutes
cleaner.registerChannel(channel, 10 * 60 * 1000);</source>

        <p>Unregistering of the channel is very straightforward:</p>

<source>
// Unregister channel
cleaner.unregisterChannel(channel);</source>

        <p>The call of this method guaraties that channel will never be processed again before it is
        added back. However, if channel was under processing when unregistering was requested the
        processing of channel will not be stopped for integrity reasons. It should pass full
        processing cycle in any case.</p>

      </section>

      <section name="Cleaning channel immediately">

        <p>At any time user or your application may decide to clean the channel out of normal
        clean plan. For this particular case there&apos;s a method which instructs scheduler to
        fire clean event immediately and rebuild entire plan of cleans for this channel taking
	      current moment in time as starting point. Here is the code:</p>

<source>
// Trigger immediate cleaning and rebuild updates plan
cleaner.cleanChannel(channel);</source>

      </section>

      <section name="Changing global cleaning period setting">

        <p>By now you already know that Cleaner has its own global cleans period setting.
        It applies the setting to all new registrations having no custom period defined. It might
        be necessary to your application to change this setting to fit better its needs. Changing
        can happen at any time and guaranties intellectual behavior.</p>

        <p>The change will reflect in rescheduling of all currently registered channels.
        Rescheduling doesn&apos;t simply resets all of the plans (if it did this way we could end up
        with immediate cleaning of all registered channels and this is definitely not what we want),
        but evaluates if time to clean each of the channels has come (channels are older than age
        specified by new period). If so then the cleaning event will be fired. In any case the
        plan of channels will be updated with new period setting in mind. Intelligence of this
        sort ensures that Poller will not overload CPU with massive processing.</p>

        <p>Here&apos;s the code:</p>

<source>
// Set global cleans period to 5 minutes.
cleaner.setPeriod(5 * 60 * 1000);</source>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section name="Things to note">

      <ul>

        <li>You should carefully choose settings for periods. Too often updates may bring overload
        to CPU.</li>

        <li>You should remember that if you have several Matchers <i>single positive</i> vote is
        enough to fire event about that unwanted item found.</li>

	      <li>Cleaner is supposed to be thread-safe. You can count on it.</li>

      </ul>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
