<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <meta revision="$Id: faq.xml 769 2005-09-18 14:21:44Z spyromus $"/>
  <properties>
    <author email="niko@nava.de">Niko Schmuck</author>
    <title>FAQ</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>

    <section name="How do I parse a newsfeed from a file?">
      <p>
        We assume that you know that you have a newsfeed available as a
        file in a supported format (currently RSS 0.91, 1.0 and 2.0 are
        supported). Reading in a newsfeed is then really as simple as:
      </p>
<source>
import java.io.File;
import de.nava.informa.core.ChannelIF;
import de.nava.informa.impl.basic.ChannelBuilder;
import de.nava.informa.parsers.FeedParser;
...
File inpFile = new File("javanews.xml");
ChannelIF channel = FeedParser.parse(new ChannelBuilder(), inpFile);
</source>
      <p>
        For accessing the news items please look into the <a
        href="apidocs/de/nava/informa/core/ChannelIF.html">JavaDoc for
        ChannelIF</a>.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section name="How do I parse a newsfeed from an URL?">
      <p>
        Very similar solution to the previous question, here is the code
        fragment (replace fooURL with your URL object):
      </p>
<source>
ChannelIF channel = FeedParser.parse(channelBuilder, fooURL);
</source>
    </section>

    <section name="Does the API support dynamic discovery of the format
      of a newsfeed?">
      <p>
        Yes, normally you don't have to care about the channel format, since
        the FeedParser takes the format into account. The format of the
        channel can be retrieved with ChannelIF.getFormat().
      </p>
      <p>
        It is also possible to determine the channel format without parsing
        the complete feed, but analysing the root element. Here is an
        example how the <a href="apidocs/de/nava/informa/utils/FormatDetector.html">
        FormatDetector</a> could be used:
      </p>
<source>
import de.nava.informa.core.ChannelFormat;
import de.nava.informa.utils.FormatDetector;
...
ChannelFormat format = FormatDetector.getFormat(fooURL);
</source>
    </section>

    <section name="I want to order the news items chronologically, but how?">
      <p>
        For this purpose please use the ItemComparator (see <a
        href="apidocs/de/nava/informa/utils/ItemComparator.html">JavaDoc</a>)
        which allows you to sort news item in ascending (oldest
        entries first, this is the default setting) or descending
        order. You can also set (optionally) if you want the retrieve
        date or the original date (as specified in the channel
        definition) to be used, with the later assumed as default
        behaviour.
      </p>
      <p>
        The following example should clearify the usage:
      </p>
<source>
import de.nava.informa.utils.ItemComparator;
...
// convert from List to Array
Object[] items = channel.getItems().toArray();
// sort news items (latest entry first)
java.util.Arrays.sort(items, new ItemComparator(true));        
</source>
    </section>

    
    <section name="What is a good starting point to learn more about the API?">
      <p>
        I would highly recommend to have a look into the source code
        of the ChannelRegistry class (<a
        href="apidocs/de/nava/informa/utils/ChannelRegistry.html">JavaDoc</a>)
        where you might get an idea how to use channel collections in
        your own code. 
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="How do I read and parse secured feeds?">
      <p>
        Fortunately, Java SDK has everything for this already. All you have to do
        is specify your default Authenticator which will be
        queried when username and password are required to access restricted
        domains. It's very convenient mechanism and it allows lots of fun things
        to be build on top of it: dialog boxes, password repositories
        and etc. To get started quickly, try adding the following line to your
        application and access the secured feed after that (note that it will open dialog
        box, so better you weren't running it on server side):
      </p>
<source>
Authenticator.setDefault(new PluginAuthenticator());
</source>
      <p>
        Of course, this implementation isn't perfect -- it's just default.
        To do better, create your own implementation.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Why is my question not covered here?">
      <p>
        Due to lack of time the documentation is not complete yet.
        Please study the source code and
        especially the test cases (in the directory test/src) in the meantime.
        If you are willing to help out to improve documenation
        please contact the informa-developer mailing list.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
