<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <meta revision="$Id: index.xml 831 2007-01-06 22:52:57Z niko_schmuck $"/>
  <properties>
    <author email="niko@nava.de">Niko Schmuck</author>
    <title>Overview</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>

    <section name="What is Informa?">
      <p>
        The goal of the Informa Project is to provide a
        news aggregation library based on the Java Platform.  
	
        The idea was born by the authors of two Java news reader
        applications (<a
        href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/hotsheet">HotSheet</a> and <a
        href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jsurfer">Risotto</a>). We
        intended to unify the common parts into a library which can be used by
        any developer who needs to address those issues in their
        application.	
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="What is the scope of Informa?">
      <p>
        With Informa we enable you with a harmonised view on a news
        channel object model. Both channels and news items do have
        metadata assigned, it does not make any difference from which
        channel format they were originally retrieved (RSS 0.9x, RSS
        1.0 / RDF, RSS 2.0, Atom 0.3 and Atom 1.0).
      </p>
      <p>
        To ease finding relevant news items an integration
        with the full-text search
        engine (Jakarta's <a
        href="http://jakarta.apache.org/lucene/">Lucene</a>) 
        may be used optionally.
      </p>
      <p>
        Besides exporting news channels in a specified XML format
        there is a persistence backend available using the <a
        href="http://hibernate.sourceforge.net/">Hibernate</a> O/R
        mapping framework. This allows to persist the whole object
        model into a JDBC-compliant relational database. As default
        database <a href="http://hsqldb.sourceforge.net/">HypersonicSQL</a>
        was chosen, because it is very easy to embed.

        Alternatively you may want to give the other persistent backend based on <a
        href="http://castor.exolab.org/">Castor JDO</a> storage
        mechanism a try (from Informa release 0.7.0 not any longer supported).
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="What is the status of Informa?">
      <p>
        Currently, Informa is in beta state, but
        it is quite stable and fully usable. You are very welcome to
        send in feature requests or bug reports (preferably through
        the sourceforge pages).
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Informa License">
      <p>
        Informa is licensed under the <a
        href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/lgpl-license.html">GNU
        Library or "Lesser" Public License</a> (LGPL).
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Contact">
      <p>
        Any questions? Contact <a
        href="mailto:niko at nava dot de">Niko Schmuck</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>
