<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <meta revision="$Id: persistence_manager.xml 747 2005-01-28 15:45:08Z spyromus $"/>
  <properties>
    <author email="spyromus@users.sourceforge.net">Aleksey Gureev</author>
    <title>Persistence Manager</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>

    <section name="General">
      <p>
        At a present moment Informa library is providing wide variety of parsers.
        It also allows user to store his groups of channels, channels, items and
        other objects in persistent storages using Hiberate and JDO interfaces. 
        However, there are some problems with the implementations. Despite the
        fact that all of implementations have similar interfaces for helper classes
        (<i>ChannelBuilderIF</i> and etc) and objects (<i>ChannelGroupIF</i> and
        etc), they still should be handled in implementation specific way. This
        means that if you wish to migrate from in-memory storage model to Hibernate
        you should be ready to change your client application code significantly.
      </p>
      <p>
        Persistence Manager module is intended to hide the internal implementation
        complexities from developer and provide unified and well-defined interface
        to all persistent services. Persistence Manager itself will take care of
        initialization, transactions management and other specific things. It is
        also intended to solve the other big problem - multi-threading. Great number
        of applications suffer from incorrect work with persistence models in
        multi-threaded environment, having many unsynchronized sessions and objects
        floating in heap.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Module structure">
      <p>
        Structure of the module is extremely simple. Base part of the module has
        only two classes and one interface:
        <ul>
          <li><i>PersistenceManagerIF</i> - main interface of any Persistence
            Manager. This interface defines contract between client application
            and persistence management implementation. Interface provides methods,
            which are necessary to create groups of channels, channels and items,
            populate groups with channels and channels with items, delete each of
            them and perform some other valuable manipulations. The main benefit
            is that you don&apos;t need to know how things work internally, you
            just need to know what you wish to do.</li>
          <li><i>PersistenceManagerConfig</i> - configuration storage. This is
            the factory for <i>PersistenceManagerIF</i> implementations. You can
            use this class to get manager object at run-time without knowing what
            implementation is used in particular. In other words, you specify what
            implementation to use by setting system properties and do not hard-code
            the names of classes and packages in code.</li>
          <li><i>PersistenceManagerException</i> - type of exception, thrown in
            error cases by <i>PersistenceManagerIF</i>.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Working with Persistence Manager">

      <section name="Initialization">
        <p>
          By initialization the process of establishing ready to use object of
          <i>PersistenceManagerIF</i> type is meant. There are two general ways
          to get one for yourself:
          <ul>
            <li>Create it manually using constructor of particular Manager.</li>
            <li>Get it from <i>PersistenceManagerConfig</i>.</li>
          </ul>
        </p>

        <section name="Creating manager manually">
          <p>
            This method isn&apos;t good as you hard-code the name of
            implementation class in your application. In order to change
            implementation you will need to rebuild whole application (or module).
            This is how it&apos;s done on practice.
          </p>
          <source>PersistenceManagerIF manager = new de.nava.informa.utils.manager.memory.PersistenceManager();</source>
        </section>

        <section name="Getting manager from PersistenceManagerConfig">
          <p>
            This way of establishing manager object is much more flexible. During
            initialization <i>PersistenceManagerConfig</i> object (which is
            following <b>Singleton</b> pattern) reads the value of 
            <i>informa.persistencemanager</i> system property. This property
            can hold the name of class implementing <i>PersistenceManagerIF</i>.
            Here&apos;s how you can define the name of class on startup.
          </p>
<source>
java -cp ... \
  -Dinforma.persistencemanager=de.nava.informa.utils.manager.memory.PersistenceManager \
  my.app.Main</source>
          <p>
            <i>In this example we specify that in-memory implementation required.</i>
          </p>
          <p>
            The other way to specify necessary class is passing its name at
            run-time using appropriate method of <i>PersistenceManagerConfig</i>
            class.
          </p>
          <source>setPersistenceManagerClassName("de.nava.informa.utils.manager.memory.PersistenceManager");</source>
        </section>
        <p>
          <i>This piece of code initializes the same manager.</i>
        </p>
        <p>
          When initialization is done in one of these ways you can get your manager
          by making a direct call to configuration object:
        </p>
        <source>PersistenceManagerIF manager = PersistenceManagerConfig.getPersistenceManager();</source>
        <p>
          Now that you have manager object what you can do with it? Many things.
          Lets create some channels for the start.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section name="Creating channels">
        <p>
          Channels in Informa are rich on properties, but to create channel you
          need to know only few things: its title and location. Without these
          two properties channels have no practical meaning. Lets create one.
        </p>
        <source>
URL url = new URL("http://my.home.net/rss.xml");
ChannelIF newChannel = manager.createChannel("My home blog", url);</source>
        <p>
          <i>Creating the channel doesn&apos;t mean that it will be automatically
          populated with items from the given location. This only means that it
          will be stored in persistent storage. You should take care of reading
          channels&apos; data yourself, using Informa parsers or by means of
          another convenient utility module - Poller (check 
          de.nava.informa.utils.poller package).</i>
        </p>
        <p>
          Now you have your new channel. Lets add some items to it.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section name="Creating items">
        <p>
          Items cannot live on their own in wild nature, they should always
          have parent channel. As we already have one, created in the previous
          step, we can proceed to creation of items. The simplest form is
          when item has only the title. So, necessary minimum is title.
        </p>
        <source>ItemIF newItem = manager.createItem(newChannel, "Item title");</source>
        <p>
          This command creates new item and puts it into the channel.
        </p>
        <p>
          There is another way to create item. Sometimes it&apos;s necessary
          to duplicate existing item by copying all of its properties. It can
          be done easily by calling appropriate item creation method of manager.
        </p>
        <source>ItemIF newItem = manager.createItem(newChannel, itemToCopy);</source>
      </section>

      <section name="Creating groups of channels">
        <p>
          Sometimes it&apos;s necessary to organize the channels into groups.
          Each channel can reside in several groups and can also live on its
          own without any groups associated. To create empty group you should
          make the following call.
        </p>
        <source>ChannelGroupIF newGroup = manager.createGroup("My new group");</source>
        <p>
          To assign the channel to this new group you should make another call.
        </p>
        <source>manager.addChannelToGroup(newChannel, newGroup);</source>
        <p>
          Later you may decide to remove channel from group. Do so by third
          call.
        </p>
        <source>manager.removeChannelFromGroup(newChannel, newGroup);</source>
      </section>

      <section name="Merging groups">
        <p>
          You might need to move channels from one group to another, avoiding
          duplicates, and delete one of the groups. This is called merging.
          Assume that we have <i>groupA</i> and <i>groupB</i>. We wish to leave
          with only <i>groupA</i> aboard, having all channels from <i>groupB</i>
          in it. This is how we can reach our goal.
        </p>
        <source>manager.mergeGroups(groupA, groupB);</source>
      </section>

      <section name="Deleting groups">
        <p>
          When deleting groups only group objects are removed from storage.
          It&apos;s because channels can live alone, not being in any groups.
          Here&apos;s how groups are deleted.
        </p>
        <source>manager.deleteGroup(group);</source>
      </section>

      <section name="Deleting channels">
        <p>
          This topic is going after groups intentionally. You should first
          learn the basics of grouping to understand how deleting of channels
          works. When channel is deleted it&apos;s automatically removed from
          all groups it currently in. Also, all items of the channel are also
          removed from persistent storage. This means that the mentioned
          objects are no longer valid persistent entities and manager may start
          throwing exceptions (if it has no means of handling non-stored
          entities) if you will try to continue performing operations over
          them. To delete channel make a call to manager.
        </p>
        <source>manager.deleteChannel(channel);</source>
      </section>

      <section name="Deleting items">
        <p>
          Deleting items is very simple. Also has no pitfalls.
        </p>
        <source>manager.deleteItem(item);</source>
      </section>

      <section name="Getting groups, channels and items">
        <p>
          Well, by this moment we know how to create several entities, but how
          we can get these entities back when we restart our application? Each
          of the entities provides methods to get their children. You can get
          list of channels from group and list of items from channel. The only
          thing left to learn is how to get the list of groups. Manager can
          give it to you.
        </p>
        <source>ChannelGroupIF[] groups = manager.getGroups();</source>
        <p>
          Attentive reader may ask, about getting the list of channels which
          are not in groups? Yes, by this moment manager interface has no
          method to get the list of groupless channels. You can simply avoid
          these situations by using default group to keep "ungrouped"
          channels in it.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section name="Updating groups, channels and items">
        <p>
          Here comes the tricky part. It&apos;s always welcome if you notify
          manager about changes in objects. Of course, it&apos;s not necessary
          to tell manager about operations you just did by it&apos;s own means,
          but you&apos;d better tell it when you make your own modifications
          (changing title of channels, or manipulating read state of an item
          and others). It&apos;s a very simple rule. In most cases forgetting
          to notify manager about changes will not be a big problem and next
          time you will request some operation over your objects manager will
          try to update the database according to noticed changes, but
          you&apos;d better do not rely on this much. First, because it&apos;s
          not reliable enough for some implementations (for example, Hibernate).
          And second, some of implementations will require significantly more
          operations to parse your objects hierarchy in searching these changes.
        </p>
        <p>
          You may ask: "<i>Why are you haven&apos;t made automatic
          changes detection if it&apos;s so vital?</i>". Answering...
          Because if we will detect each particular change in sequence of 100
          modifications we will have 100 update statements. And if we will
          make all of our modifications and then notify the manager we will 
          have significantly less of them. Moreover, we can have even single
          statement if all the changes were made on behalf of single object.
        </p>
        <p>
          This is how we do our updates:
        </p>
<source>
URL url = new URL("http://my.home.net/rss.xml");
ChannelIF newChannel = manager.createChannel("My home blog", url);

...

// Update and notify manager
newChannel.setTitle("Some new title");
manager.updateChannel(newChannel);

// The similar picture with groups and channels
manager.updateGroup(someGroup);
manager.updateItem(someItem);</source>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="Limitations">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>Current version supports only groups (<i>ChannelGroupIF</i>),
            channels (<i>ChannelIF</i>) and items (<i>ItemIF</i>). It&apos;s
            not planned to extend the library by now as it looks sufficient
            for the most applications to have only these three kinds of
            entities.</li>
          <li>When working with manager make sure that you are not using
            externally created objects of the types understood by manager. For
            example, you may have some <i>ChannelIF</i> objects unserialized
            from XML or created manually. Using them with manager will not
            work. Manager implementation is free to support these cases, but
            it also free to not to do so. Please be careful with where you
            get your objects.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
