<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <meta revision="$Id: poller.xml 746 2005-01-12 11:05:58Z spyromus $"/>
  <properties>
    <author email="spyromus@users.sourceforge.net">Aleksey Gureev</author>
    <title>Poller</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="General">

      <p>The Poller module is intended to provide convenient services for background polling of
      channel changes. Once you have some channels you might be interested in periodical check for
      updates. Poller helps to do this task common to many applications. It accepts channels for
      registration and creates the schedule for their updates.</p>

      <p>Poller uses simple, but powerful engine to work with rules. Application may define rules
      (Approvers) to decide whether the addition of separate items in channels should occur. This
      way you can filter old, unwanted or other items before they are added to the application
      database.</p>

      <p>Also it has listeners (Observers) which are notified each time interesting event occurs. By
      interesting events we mean:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>polling of channel started, finished or errored</li>
        <li>channel data updated (updated information about channel itself, not its items)</li>
        <li>new item found</li>
      </ul>

      <p>You can add as many listeners as you need and each of them will get an event notification
      from Poller.</p>

    </section>

    <section name="Module structure">

      <p>The module has very small number of classes in the package (de.nava.informa.utils.poller)
      for you to remember in order to work effectively with it:</p>

      <ul>

        <li><i>Poller</i> - the main class and central access point to all of Poller services.</li>

        <li><i>PollerApproverIF</i> - interface for Approver implementations. Each Approver added to
        Poller will be consulted each time new item found in registered channel. Approver can
        approve or deny addition of newly found item to the channel. If you have several
        Approvers installed then <i>all</i> of them should vote for addition or item will not
        be added.</li>

        <li><i>PollerObserverIF</i> - interface for Observer implementation. Each Observer added to
        Poller will be notified each time some event occurs over registered channel. Events are
        specified briefly in previous section.</li>

      </ul>

      <p>In addition there is additional convenience class provided for transferring changes into
      Informa persistent storage. <i>PersistenceObserver</i> listens to all events coming from
      Poller and performs consequent changes to underlying storage using manager specified on
      construction. Note that if you plan to use it instances of channels Poller will be dealing
      with should be produced by Persistence Manager. Otherwise they will not be understood by it
      and you can get confusing results.</p>

    </section>

    <section name="Working with Poller">

      <section name="Initialization">

        <p>Initialization of Poller is very simple. You create new instance of Poller and it starts
        to work right away. Here&apos;s the code for that:</p>

        <source>Poller poller = new Poller();</source>

        <p>Default period of polls is set to one hour. You can change it and we will show a bit
        later how.</p>

        <p>Poller is capable of doing its work in multiple threads. Doing so it dramatically
        increases performance of polling. Default value of number of working threads is
        determined by underlying scheduler. At the moment of this writing the default is set to
        <i>5</i> threads, but it may change, though it&apos;s not likely to. In most cases you
        do not need to deal with such a details, but if you really need full control over that you
        can specify number of working threads on creation or change it at run-time.</p>

<source>
// Here we create a single-threaded Poller
Poller poller = new Poller(1);

// Here we change number of threads to 3
poller.setWorkerThreads(3);</source>

        <p>You should note that change from bigger number of threads down to smaller can take some
        time. It&apos;s not time of the method call itself, but a time of transition. It works
        this way because the threads requiring to be removed can be busy with processing at the
        time of change and engine will wait for completion before killing them.</p>

        <p>In addition, you can control how Poller behaves when scanning the feed for a new items.
        The parameter is called "item scanning policy", specified during Poller construction and
        can have the following values:</p>

        <ul>
          <li><i>POLICY_SCAN_ALL</i> - default policy meaning that Poller will walk throught the
            whole feed.</li>
          <li><i>POLICY_SKIP_AFTER_EXISTING</i> - this policy means that Poller will stop checking
            items once it finds the already existing one. It's helpful to save time spent on
            checking old items, but hardly relies on the fact that we cannot see anything useful
            after the existing items.</li>
        </ul>

<source>
// Here we create a single-threaded Poller with specific item scanning policy
Poller poller = new Poller(1, Poller.POLICY_SKIP_AFTER_EXISTING);</source>

      </section>

      <section name="Observers">

        <p>Observers, as it was described before, receive notifications on interesting events:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>start of polling;</li>
          <li>finish of polling;</li>
          <li>abnormal termination of polling because of errors;</li>
          <li>chang in channel information;</li>
          <li>finding of new items.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>From the list of events it becomes clear what lifecycle of the channel processing looks
	like. One necessary note is that only one of events (whether &apos;finish of polling&apos;
	or &apos;abnormal termination&apos;) can be fired on completion.</p>

        <p>Another note is that Poller is not adding new items to the channels for itself. One of
        your observers should take care of it.</p>

        <p>Once you have instance of Poller you need to register at least one observer to make it
        useful. Here&apos;s the piece of code:</p>

<source>
Poller poller = new Poller();

// Create and register observer
PollerObserverIF observer = new MyObserver();
poller.addObserver(observer);</source>

        <p>You may need to remove some observer from the list and you can do it this way:</p>

        <source>poller.removeObserver(observer);</source>

      </section>

      <section name="Approvers">

        <p>Approvers are very simple by their nature. They have a single method which is called by
        worker threads of Poller when they find some new items in channels. Approver should give
        an answer to them if it likes new item and approves it to be added.</p>

        <p>Adding and removing of approvers is also simple:</p>

<source>
// Adding new approver
PollerApproverIF approver = new MyApprover();
poller.addApprover(approver);

// Removing approver
poller.removeApprover(approver);</source>

      </section>

      <section name="Registering and unregistering channels">

        <p>The next step after you have created Poller instance and set all necessary observers
        and approvers is to register some channels. When you register channel Poller contacts
        underlying scheduler to create plan of updates for the channel. The first checking of
	the channel will start right after that.</p>

<source>
// Register channel with default polling period
poller.registerChannel(channel);</source>

        <p>It was the code which registers new channel. Simple, isn&apos;t it?</p>

        <p>By default, Poller uses its global period setting (which is equal to one hour) to
        initialize channel and build the updates plan with scheduler, but you may wish to specify
        your own period for each particular channel.</p>

<source>
// Register channel with polling period set to 10 minutes
poller.registerChannel(channel, 10 * 60 * 1000);</source>

        <p>Unregistering of the channel is very straightforward:</p>

<source>
// Unregister channel
poller.unregisterChannel(channel);</source>

        <p>The call of this method guaraties that channel will never be processed again before it is
        added back. However, if channel was under processing when unregistering was requested the
        processing of channel will not be stopped for integrity reasons. It should pass full
        processing cycle in any case.</p>

      </section>

      <section name="Updating channel immediately">

        <p>At any time user or your application may decide to update the channel out of normal
        update plan. For this particular case there&apos;s a method which instructs scheduler to
        fire update event immediately and rebuild entire plan of updates for this channel taking
	      current moment in time as starting point. Here is the code:</p>

<source>
// Trigger immediate updating and rebuild updates plan
poller.updateChannel(channel);</source>

      </section>

      <section name="Changing global update period setting">

        <p>By now you already know that Poller has its own global updates period setting. It applies
        the setting to all new registrations having no custom period defined. It might be necessary to
        your application to change this setting to fit better its needs. Changing can happen at
        any time and guaranties intellectual behavior.</p>

        <p>The change will reflect in rescheduling of all currently registered channels.
        Rescheduling doesn&apos;t simply resets all of the plans (if it did this way we could end up
        with immediate update of all registered channels and this is definitely not what we want),
        but evaluates if time to update each of the channels has come (channels are older than age
        specified by new period). If so then the update event will be fired. In any case the
        plan of channels will be updated with new period setting in mind. Intelligence of this
        sort ensures that Poller will not overload the network or CPU in any case.</p>

        <p>Here&apos;s the code:</p>

<source>
// Set global updates period to 5 minutes.
poller.setPeriod(5 * 60 * 1000);</source>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section name="Things to note">

      <ul>

        <li>You should carefully choose settings for periods. Too often updates may bring overload
        to network.</li>

        <li>You should remember that if you have several Approvers <i>all</i> of them must vote for
        item in order to make Poller fire itemFound event.</li>

	      <li>Poller is supposed to be thread-safe. You can count on it.</li>
      </ul>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
